<sidebar>
  <title>Compass Goal</title>
  <para><emphasis>"Simplify the integration of Search Engine into any application"</emphasis></para>
  <para>As you will see, Compass is geared towards integrating Search Engine functionality into any type of application (web app, rich client, middle-ware, ...). We ask you, the user, to give feedback on how complex it was to integrate Compass into your application, and places where Compass can be enhanced to make things even simpler.</para>
</sidebar>
   
<para>Compass is a powerful, transactional Java Search Engine framework. Compass allows you to declaratively map your Object domain model to the underlying Search Engine, synchronizing data changes between search engine index and different datasources. Compass provides a high level abstraction on top of the Lucene low level API. Compass also implements fast index operations and optimization and introduces transaction capabilities to the Search Engine.</para>

<para>
Compass aim is to provide the following:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The simplest solution for enabling search capabilities within your application stack.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Promote the use of Search Engine as a lightweight application datasource.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Provide rich Search Engine semantics to find application data.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Synchronize data changes between Search Engine and different datasources.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Write less code, find data quicker.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
  This document provides a reference guide to Compass's features. Since this document is still to be considered very much work-in-progress, if you have any requests or comments, please post them on Compass forum, or Compass JIRA (issue tracking).
</para>

<para>
  Before we continue, the Compass team would like to thank the <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org">Spring Framework</ulink> teams, for providing the template DocBook definition and configuration, which help us create this reference guide.
</para>