<chapter id="samples-library">

    <title>Library Sample</title>

    <sect1 id="samples-library-introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>
            Compass::Samples [library] is a basic example, that highlights the main features of Compass::Core. The application contains a small library domain model, containing <literal>Author</literal>, <literal>Article</literal> and <literal>Book</literal> Objects.
        </para>

        <para>
            You can find most of Compass::Core features used within the library sample, such as OSEM and Common Metadata. It executes as a unit test, using <ulink url="http://junit.org">JUnit</ulink> and can be used to search a predefined set of data. Modify the <literal>LibraryTests</literal> class to add your own test data and experiment with how easy it is to work with Compass. Enjoy.
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="samples-library-running">
        <title>Running The Sample</title>

        <para>
            Running the library sample, you will need to have <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org">Apache Ant</ulink> installed and have ANT_HOME/bin on your path. The following table lists the available ant targets.

            <table>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="3*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="5*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Target</entry><entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>usage (also the default target)</entry>
                        <entry>Lists all the available targets.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>test</entry>
                        <entry>Runs the tests defined in the <literal>LibraryTests</literal>, also compiles sample (see the compile target).</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>compile</entry>
                        <entry>Compiles the tests and the source code into the build/classes directory. Also executes the common meta data task to generate the <literal>Library</literal> class out of the <literal>library.cmd.xml</literal> file into the source directory.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>search</entry>
                        <entry>Executes the <literal>LibraryTests</literal> main method, which pre-populates the index with data. You can interactivly provide a search query to execute a search on the index.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>

        </para>

    </sect1>

</chapter>
